So we've talked about CDNs,
we've talked about working with just the index.html,
but most projects are not going to be run that way.
That's just the reality.
Most people have bought in fully to the tool chain system,
and so it's time that we did so too.
For those who come from the Vue2 ecosystem,
you're probably used to scaffolding your app with Vue CLI.
But there's been a new kid on the block in terms of
the whole webpack build tool chain,
and if you haven't heard about it, it's called Vue.
One of the great things about Vue,
basically what you need to know is that it's a bundler underneath
that's helping to push front-end tooling to use more ES modules.
Basically, it helps to make apps more performant.
What's really nice about Vue though, as well,
is that even though EvanU, the creator of Vue,
is one of the founders of the Vue technology,
it's a multi-framework tooling.
So it's really nice to see a lot of frameworks starting to gather around it.
So for anyone who's interested in this kind of stuff and want to see
like helping to create plugins so that other frameworks can leverage that,
Vue is doing a very good job as far as bringing the community together.
But because of all these performance optimizations though,
Vue CLI currently still uses a webpack and so it basically is being deprecated in
favor of the createVue which is the new basically equivalent of Vue CLI.
For this one, this has Vue powering it underneath.
So this is where the shift is.
So going forward, if you're creating a new Vue 3 app and you have
the luxury of using Vue underneath,
createVue is the basically recommended way going forward.
So let's go ahead and create a project and see what that looks like, shall we?
To do that, we're going to run the command NPM createVue3 inside of our project.
So I'm going to go ahead and just close some of this off now,
and let's go ahead and open this up.
NPM createVue at 3.
So one of the things that's really nice about
the modern built tool chains these days is that you don't have to
install a massive CLI on your computer only to use it a couple of times,
maybe like a year or something.
It's being called on the fly because NPM knows,
you want to temporarily install something,
I'll basically bring down the package,
I'll use it and after that it won't be on your machine anymore.
So for this one, I'm just going to call mine Sandbox right now because I want to
show you all what's inside and then you all will have
an opportunity to create your own building on what we've been doing today.
All right, so I've named it Sandbox,
and so at first glance, you see at TypeScript,
your first impression might be,
I'm definitely not using TypeScript, hit no.
I'm going to say hit yes,
and the short reason for that is
because when Vue gives you the option to add the TypeScript,
what it's saying is it's not saying you have to use TypeScript,
it's saying we're going to configure everything so that if you ever choose to use TypeScript,
it's really easy, no configuration needed kind of it.
There'll be one or two lines of code we'll add to make it basically
like ignore any TypeScript errors,
but one of the things that I found that's really
painful when it comes to code migrations is that
people who want to start sprinkling in TypeScript,
usually the build tool chain is what blocks them from doing that because they're like,
oh, I just want to try types and then it's like,
oh, you have to look at this config file,
then you have to do a TS config and then by the time they've looked like
that obstacle it's getting started can be super expensive.
If you didn't know, there's a Vue3 and TypeScript workshop that I did,
so you can watch that separately.
But generally speaking,
what I'm saying here is that this is great for
code bases in the sense that if one person wants to use types on one file,
they can, you don't have to enforce it across the entire code base,
and that's the benefit of having that configured.
As you can see here, JSX support,
this is something I do want to address especially for those coming from the React background,
is that you can use JSX with Vue.
You've been seeing us do a lot with native HTML,
but just know that if you really love JSX and you don't want to use native HTML,
you can still do that.
But personally, I do find it's advantageous to use native HTML,
but just know that Vue can totally support that if that's something you prefer.
We're not going to worry about Vue Router right now or Pinia,
and we're not doing any end-to-end,
but sure, let's add ESLint and Prettier.
For those who are new to the tools chain space,
ESLint is basically and Prettier are ways to
standardize how your code is formatted and how it looks.
So things like whether tabs are two spaces,
four spaces or actual tabs, semicolons,
those sort of things, that's how you can enforce consistency across your code base.
So let's take a look at what's actually in here.
So inside of my Sandbox directory,
you now see a standard Vue project that scaffolded in Vue.
So a couple of things here.
One, we have a source directory,
which is fairly standard on front-end client framework apps these days.
We have the public directory,
which is going to be what's served basically to users.
So basically, think of the public directory as
the build tools will not do anything to it,
it will just be bundled with your code when you serve it.
So basically no asset optimization, none of that.
Then what we can see here as well is we have an index.html,
and this is where you can see actually how your code is basically being built.
In the sense that like if you want to drop Google font libraries,
it's as simple now as coming into your index.html file and just dropping in
your link to your style sheets, whatever you need.
Then here we can see we have our div app as well,
and then script type module here main.ts,
and this main.ts refers to this file inside of our source directory.
So you can see this should look actually pretty familiar.
We're importing the create app helper method from Vue,
and then we're creating an app with that,
and then we're mounting it to the div ID right here.
So that's where you see that inside of index.
Actually, let me split this window so that we can get them side by side.
So there we go.
This is where these two are talking to each other,
and then you'll notice that we're also importing some CSS as well,
and I'll talk more to this in a little bit.
Okay. So to show you just that everything works,
let me go ahead and go inside of the sandbox,
and I'm going to install the dependencies by running npm install.
So while we're doing that,
what I'd like people to do is if you look up Vue DevTools on
your browser, whether it's Chrome,
Firefox should have it as well,
you should get an extension that you should be able to install here.
So Vue.js DevTools, you'll see it has about
1,800 at the time of this recording,
and so you'll want to install this because this is what's actually showing up here.
So if you click on your extensions,
you can go ahead and pin it if it's hidden right now for you,
because we'll be using that to explore what
the Vue DevTools does for us when it comes to looking at a Vue project.
Okay. So inside of here,
we can see everything is running now.
So we look at package.json now,
and see what commands we have available to us.
Well, we have the ability to dev, okay?
Then there's a bunch of typescript stuff,
we're not even going to worry about that right now.
So npm run dev. All right, great.
Let's open that up. There we go.
As we can see, this is your Hello World Vue application.
Now, when we take a look now,
you'll notice that the DevTools,
if you have that installed,
will actually go ahead and light up.
So if you open up your console now,
and you go into the drop-down,
or if you have a really wide monitor,
you might already see it,
but mine is hidden since it's a little bit bigger.
Click on Vue, you'll see that here we go.
We have the dev item.
Basically, our entire app now is able to be inspected inside of here.
So what we're seeing here is basically,
we're starting to introduce the idea of components, right?
Components-driven development is really popular in
today's modern front-end frameworks.
So as you would expect,
Vue certainly supports components and we'll be
doing a lot more with that now that
we have the built-in training supported.
So what's cool about this is that you can see,
as you click on the different components,
it'll actually tell you a little bit about it.
So you can see that, oh, yes, here in the welcome,
there's a bunch of stuff being set up.
The Hello World here has a message,
like we'll be using this a lot to
inspect what's going on underneath the components.
So definitely keep this in mind when we start to
move forward on other things.
So what we're going to do is I'm going to go ahead and
port over the playground that I had made,
and we're going to go ahead and actually use
that to create the app to show you what's going on.
So the main thing to understand here is that inside of
the main.ts, you'll see here inside of this app Vue.
So dot Vue files are the bread and butter
of one of the reasons why I think Vue also got really popular,
and so these are called single file components.
So they're single file components because,
well, they have a lot going on.
What you might notice though is that none of
my syntax highlighting is working,
and the reason for that is because you need to actually
enable a VS Code extension,
and the one that I recommend,
actually it's kind of the standard actually,
is Volar, V-O-L-A-R.
So if you're using VS Code,
go ahead and install that on your machine while you're at it.
So I'm going to go ahead and enable mine,
and it does a ton of stuff for you.
Honestly, there could probably be
a half day lecture just on Volar alone,
but know that it helps you out with
syntax highlighting and a couple of other things as well.
Okay. So instead of app.vue,
you might notice this should look pretty familiar to you.
In the sense that, okay,
we have this part here, this template,
this is HTML, and this template element,
believe it or not, is actually built on a standard in HTML.
The template element is actually
a built-in thing to HTML, it's not just a Vue thing.
But basically it says, hey,
this is the HTML that I'm managing in this specific file.
The script block is what you expect.
Here's the JavaScript that I'm managing,
and here we even have a style block,
and that's to manage all the CSS.
So as you can see, the reason why it's called
single file components is because it basically allows you to
scope all the things that you care about into a single file.
That might sound like,
what's so special about that,
but we have to remember prior to this,
a lot of times what people were doing is they would
have an app.html, for example, for the template.
They'd have an app.js for the JavaScript,
and then they have an app.css for the CSS.
To some extent, there's nothing wrong with that architecture,
but for a lot of us who like,
especially when you're navigating back between files,
it's actually really helpful just to have it all in one place.
At least that's what I found in my experience.
Now granted, there's nothing stopping you
from choosing your own adventure.
So all these blocks here, they're optional.
So I can delete this and we can just have,
we can only use the template and the script.
The other thing that people often
misunderstand when it comes to single file components as well,
is that the script, template,
and style blocks are just what's default out of the box.
There are actually other libraries and plugins
that utilize things like a docs plugin.
So it'll use a docs tag wrapper,
and then basically whatever you document there will
be associated with that specific component.
So really, it's actually an open canvas
for people's imaginations when it comes to how they might want
to scope, how information is being managed
across their code base.
All right, so let's go ahead and migrate
some stuff over, shall we?
So I'm gonna go ahead and open up my playground here.
Let's do that and then switch that over here.
All right, let me zoom out a little bit,
so I think it's a little bit harder, wait, can I zoom in?
Yeah, that's a little bit harder, here we go.
Okay, so I'm gonna go ahead and delete this boilerplate stuff.
You all will understand how this works
by the end of the workshop, so don't worry there.
But this way, we keep it simple.
We have a script block, we have a template block.
In other words, our JavaScript and our HTML.
So what we can do here is we can basically copy in
our HTML here, all the way down to the div.
And we're gonna go ahead and drop it inside of our template.
Okay, a lot of things are gonna be breaking right now,
and that's totally fine, because what we've gotta do,
we gotta copy all this data that we have here.
So we have a bunch of stuff inside of here,
and we're just gonna copy all of it.
Or in this case, I'm cutting it.
The main difference in tactically speaking though,
is that what we gotta do is rather than saying
like create app here, because the app
has already been created, we basically are saying,
let's export the object that we're gonna be using.
So in other words, here is the specific object
that will reflect the JavaScript for this file.
There we go.
Okay, so what we see here, we're back to the point
where we have our data here, and we have all the stuff
that we just copy pasted, and we have our template.
So we see some stuff yelling at us, yep,
we'll talk about that in a little bit.
And so let's see if this actually did anything for us.
So you'll notice, okay, our data is there,
it's just super messy.
The reason it's super messy is because we have,
inside of our main.ts, you saw earlier
we have this main.ts, we're gonna wipe that out.
Cause right now we just wanna work with standard things
and make sure everything's just working.
And so sure enough, there we go.
We have our app, and it's up and running.
Okay, so, the first thing I wanna address here
is that you'll notice now, before we weren't getting
any sort of errors when we did the index.html way,
because basically, volar and these sort of extensions
allow us to basically identify common problems
that people sort of, or mistakes that they make
when it comes to this stuff.
And so you'll notice here, we got these error messages here
because it's saying that whenever we iterate
through an element, it's expected to have
a vbind key directive.
And so what does that mean exactly?
Well, basically when you're having the frameworks
track the elements that they're looping through,
it's good to give them some sort of identifier
so that they know whether or not something's changed or not.
Without that identifier, you basically run the risk
of relying solely on the data to figure out what's working.
And especially when it comes to animation,
it'll bite you in the butt constantly.
And so typically what people do then
is they will do the vbind directive
because the key needs to be a unique key for everything.
And so we can also shortcut this as well
to just like this, vkey.
And then we can do something as simple as, for example,
I sometimes would just take out the index
and I'll say I will do a ES6 string,
and I'll go item-index, for example.
And so this here then basically provides a custom key.
Now most of the time when you're working with databases,
hopefully you have UUIDs and that kind of thing
to populate it, but for the sake of like
sort of demoing this at the moment,
this is how we could fulfill this requirement.
They're basically creating our own key.
So you'll see here, it notices that this is,
I think identical to the other one, but index, it doesn't.
So there you go, number, index, great.
What does it not like about it?
Oh, it'll format it.
Okay, there we go.
And just like that, we have our app now working
inside of the build tool chain.
This is the final bit that I was talking about.
Remember how I was talking about
where we've enabled TypeScript, but you don't have to use it?
The main thing here is that you'll notice
Volar is basically saying, hey,
I thought we were in TypeScript, what's going on?
So what you gotta do here is go into your tsconfig.json
and under the compiler options, we can allow js to true.
And that'll basically prevent it from yelling at us anymore
if we don't use TypeScript.
But on the other hand, if anyone ever does use TypeScript,
it's just gonna work magically.
And all the configurations already work.
Oh yes, go.
If you have an existing project,
would you probably not recommend trying to vitifize it?
So the question here is around,
if you have an existing project that already works,
whether or not to switch it over to vit.
Honestly, most of the people who've switched to tool chain
have found very little difference.
In terms of like, it's not like other build tools
where like something usually major breaks.
So I guess a lot of it boils down
to actually your dependencies.
I would take a look at that.
If you have a lot of dependencies that rely
on some sort of webpack build,
then in that case, vit might be a little premature.
But if it's a more evergreen project
where it has like standard JavaScript stuff
that it's JavaScript libraries installing
that might already have ESM support for ES modules,
then that would be a great case for like,
let's just try and see what happens
because the performance improvements
that people are experiencing on vit are pretty significant.
And so it's honestly, it's worth,
it's worth like an hour time box effort
just to see if you can improve the DX on that regard.